Please come in.
请
Grand Tutor, this is who
这位便是
you've been meaning to meet, the Empress Dowager of Northern Qin.
太傅想见的我朝太后
Your Majesty has finally shown your true face.
太后终于以真面目示人了
I have no choice.
没法子啊
Young Lord Xiao has seen right through me.
已经被你们的萧世子看穿了
Any more concealment
再藏
would be meaningless.
也就没意思了
Your Majesty feels unwell,
太后御体欠安
yet you are still personally hosting the peace talks.
还亲自来主持和谈
It is never easy to be a mother.
为母不易啊
My end is drawing near.
大限将至
I have to settle certain matters myself before my passing.
总有些身后事要亲自做
This trip of mine is
吾此行
partly
一来
for an old acquantaince,
为我的一位故人
and partly
二来
for you, Grand Tutor Xie.
则是为谢太傅
Haven't you always been wondering
谢太傅不是一直想知道
about the truth of the gruesome case where the An and Lu families
当年安陆二氏通敌
colluded with the enemy and allied with the Northern Qin's
与吾北秦右贤王
Right King of Virtue
穆连一门
from the Mulian family to establish their own administration?
合谋自立的血案真相吗
I had not yet entered the palace by then.
当年吾尚未入宫
Some things are not easy to investigate.
有些事要查可不容易
That said, I am
不过吾
willing to cooperate with you, Grand Tutor Xie.
倒是愿意与谢太傅合作
Didn't Your Majesty just say
方才太后不是说
that your end is drawing near?
自己大限将至吗
Do you think cooperation
死了
is impossible when I am dead?
便不能合作了
It is not true.
非也
Only when I am dead
有些事
can the two of us cooperate
只有吾死了
on some issues.
才能与太傅合作
Don't be so petty.
你别那么小气嘛
I know this workshop belongs to Yuan Xiaoliu.
我知道这个工坊是元小六的
I'm just borrowing it for a bit.
我就借来用一用
Frankly speaking,
你别说
this looks quite like the one at my home.
这和我们家那个还挺像
Don't all workshops look similar?
工坊不都长得差不多吗
Wait, who told you
不过谁跟你说
this was meant for Yuan Xiaoliu?
这是给元小六的了
So this is not his workshop?
不是他的吗
How could he charge me rent?
那他收我租金
Explain this.
解释一下
It's about a private job I took
这是我在妙手铺子
at the Miraculous Craft shop.
接的一个私活
The well in Honglu Temple was clogged,
说是鸿胪寺水井堵塞
so I went to clear it.
我去通了一下
What about this?
这个呢
This is for cracking sunflower seeds.
这个是用来嗑瓜子的
Look, just turn it like this,
你看啊 你就这样
and a load of seeds can be cracked.
能剥一大把瓜子
This copper ball here contains fragrances.
这个铜球是香囊
Didn't you say the people of Northern Qin eat strong-smelling food,
你不是说北秦人饮食腥膻
and thus have noticeable body odors?
体味重
If they carry this around,
把这个戴在身上
their odors can be covered,
就可以遮盖体味
and the pleasant scent in it will last for several months.
留香持久可达数月
Did you still plan to blow up the Eagle King with fire thunderstones?
难道你还想用引火雷炸了鹰王
Definitely not.
怎么可能
I...
我
Who said I went see him?
谁说我去见鹰王
That's a lie.
编
Keep lying then.
接着编
Didn't you go to meet the Eagle King
你今日不是为了李乐君
for Li Lejun today?
去找鹰王了吗
Tell me. What did you promise to give the Eagle King in exchange
说吧 为了阻止和亲
for halting the political marriage?
你跟鹰王做了什么交易
Spill it.
说
Repeating crossbows?
连弩
Gunpowder?
火药
Xie Jiayu,
谢嘉鱼
tell me what this is.
你告诉我这是什么
Don't hit me in the face!
别打脸
This is refined iron.
是精铁
And this is your so-called solution?
这就是你所谓的办法
Do you even know this will have you...
你知不知道这会让你
You're such a fool.
笨死了
I didn't trade the iron casting technique to the Eagle King.
我没和鹰王交易铸铁术
Please say something!
你倒是说句话呀
I really didn't betray Ye.
我真没出卖咱大邺
I know sometimes I can be a bit unreliable,
虽然我平时是有点不着调吧
but I'd never cross the line, would I?
但我不至于一点调都不着吧
Fine. Believe what you want.
行 你说什么是什么
Alright?
行了吧
The Eagle King agreed to set Lejun free
鹰王已经答应我了
if I offered the iron casting technique.
用铸铁术换回乐君的自由
Are you satisfied now?
行了吗
What exactly are you mad about?
你到底在气什么呀
I already told you
我都说了
I didn't sell out the iron casting technique.
我没出卖铸铁术
I was merely selling devices of my own creation.
我卖的是妙手器具
What do you mean by this?
这是何意
Your Highness, have you ever heard about the Miraculous Craft?
殿下可曾听说过妙手之名
No, never.
没听说过
This Brilliant Manual on Farm Tools records
这本《耒耜天机谱》记载了妙手
all the farm implements
也就是我
designed and improved by the Miraculous Craft, namely me.
所设计改良的所有农具
Please look at this foot-treadled water diversion tool.
殿下且观这踏犁引水术
By replacing the straight shaft with a curved one
以曲辕代替直辕
and adding three fans,
配风扇三展
it can be used to easily reclaim a hundred mu
纵是漠北碱土
of alkaline earth as farmland a day
日拓百亩
even in the northern desert region.
易如反掌
And this dragon-bone water-lifting device
此龙骨翻车
combines the wisdom of the chapter on waterways in the Record of Trades.
暗合《考工记》水道篇
It saves much manpower.
可省去大量人力
With it, even an 80-year-old woman
便是八十老妪驾此器开荒
can clear over 70 mu of wasteland.
尚耕七十余亩
Here's a bird-shaped bronze rain gauge.
还有这测雨铜仪
The beak is filled with saltpeter,
凤喙装了硝石
while the tail is inlaid with a compass.
尾羽嵌了司南
Blue smoke is guaranteed to appear
地动前三日
three days before an earthquake.
必现青烟
Sweet sorghum can be planted in the southern desert area,
漠南种甜高粱
and cold-region mulberry trees on Mount Yin,
阴山植寒地桑
with the help of iron-rimmed wooden ploughing wheels.
再辅以代耕架铁木轮
This page instructs on how to turn saline-alkali land into fertile fields.
此页记盐碱地化良田之术
Can Your Highness bear to watch the manual burned into ashes?
殿下舍得任其成灰
You!
你
You...
你这
Don't worry. I've memorized all the content.
放心 都记在我脑海里了
Although Northern Qin has occupied the Capital,
这北秦虽占领上京
your people are good at nomadism, not farming.
但却善游牧 不善农耕
Last year, 30,000 head cattle and sheep died from the cold.
去年冻毙牛羊三万头
The harvest in the fields were poor.
这田里收成也不乐观
The national treasury had few grain reserves.
国库没有存粮
The people of Northern Qin
这北秦百姓
endured quite a bitter winter.
着实过了一个苦冬啊
But now,
不过如今
I can help you break the constraints.
我可以帮你打破掣肘
As long as you call off the marriage to Li Lejun,
只要你放过李乐君
I'll gift you all the instruments
这《耒耜天机谱》中的所有器具
in the Brilliant Manual on Farm Tools.
我都可以赠予你
What do you think?
如何
Are all of these...
这些
really your inventions?
当真是你发明的
Yes, I am exactly the Miraculous Craft.
妙手如假包换
I understand
我知道
that the superior quality
精铁技术
of Beifu Army's weaponry is based on the iron casting technique.
是北府兵武器精良的根基
I simply used it a pretext
我只是拿这个
to lure the Eagle King into meeting me.
来吸引鹰王和我相见而已嘛
Xiao Wuyi, listen.
萧无衣 我跟你说
I swear,
我发誓
if I had truly traded the smelting technique for refined iron
如果我真的拿精铁冶炼技术
to the Eagle King,
出卖给鹰王
fate would have it
就叫我日后
that I get trafficked again when I leave Jiankang
出了剑慷我再被人贩子拐了
-and... -Do you need a fix
你这张嘴 而且
on that mouth of yours?
是不是欠收拾
Can't you stop saying unlucky things?
能不能有点忌讳
I was just trying
我就是表达一下
to express my loyalty to Ye.
我对大邺的忠心嘛
You have no idea what I'm mad about.
你根本不懂我在气什么
Tell me then.
那你倒是说呀
You shouldn't have shown your abilities
你就不该在鹰王面前
in front of the Eagle King.
展现你的能力
Techniques are dead, but people are alive.
技法是死的 人是活的
Have you ever considered
你可曾想过
what will happen
万一你被鹰王盯上了
if the Eagle King targets you?
你该怎么办
Aren't you planning to explore the world?
你不要去游历天下吗
When I get to the Northern Border,
届时我在北境
I'll be too far away to help you.
鞭长莫及
Should there be slight negligence
但凡有一点疏漏大意
or even just an opportunity,
哪怕是一个契机
he can capture you and take you to Northern Qin.
他都可以把你抓去北秦
Then you won't have anyone to turn to.
到时候你叫天天不应
You're not exactly the brave type.
就你这点胆量
When your life is in the palm of his hand,
小命被他捏在手里
will you ever refuse to do what he asks you?
他让你做什么你不做
Well, Mao's always there for me.
那我还有阿茂呢
He can protect me too.
他也能保护我
Indeed,
是
there is someone to protect you.
是有人保护你
I shouldn't have worried about you.
是我白操了这份闲心
The first thing you need is a lesson
你要做的第一件事
on how to intimidate others.
是学会威慑
In this regard,
这一点
Xiao Wuyi has set a good example for you.
萧无衣才是你的老师
Whether to stay or leave
是走是留
is up to you.
你自己定
Take good care of Lejun.
照顾好乐君
Greetings, Your Highness.
参见岐王殿下
Just bury this woman
随便找个地方
who thought she was Princess Qi somewhere random.
把这自以为是岐王妃的女人埋了
I request a audience with Master Cui.
我要见崔氏家主
No need to enter the premises, Your Highness.
殿下不必入府了
Master Cui will not
我们家主
meet Your Highness.
不见
Get out of my way.
让开
Would you take a look at this, Your Highness?
殿下不妨先看看这个
Master Cui knew perfectly well
我家家主早就知道
that Your Highness would surely pay a visit
殿下一定会为那
for the political marriage arranged for Princess Pingning.
平宁县主和亲之事前来
So, he insisted that I pass on a message to Your Highness,
所以一定要让我传话给您
hoping that you would put the national interests above all
希望您务必要以天下为重
and prioritize the greater good.
顾全大局呀
I must see Master Cui
今日事急
for an urgent matter today.
我必须要见到家主
Please do lend me a helping hand.
还请您通融一下
Your Highness, have some self-respect!
殿下好不自重
Do you even know this is the Cui Mansion?
你可知这里是崔府
Is Your Highness trying to
殿下这么做
ruin the Cui family's good reputation by offering bribes?
莫非是要毁我崔氏之名声吗
I do address you as Your Highness,
叫你一声殿下
but do you really think you're some precious Prince Qi?
还真拿自己当岐王了
Even Qizhou is long gone—
那岐州都没了
Princess Qi was no better than a stray dog, was she?
岐王妃不也是只丧家之犬吗
Mother!
阿母
What did you say?
你说什么
I said...
我说
Answer me!
我问你
What did you just say?
你方才说什么
Well, actually, I didn't...
我其实我也没
I am the Regent now.
我乃当今监国
Step forward, I dare you!
谁敢上前
Years ago, Empress Wenxi
当年文熹皇后
was incomparably capable.
何等惊才绝艳
She single-handedly helped the nobles migrate to the south safely.
以一己之力护宗室南渡
How come the nowadays Cui family
怎么如今的崔氏
is filled with selfish and cowardly gits
竟人人都是自私自利
terrified of death?
贪生怕死之徒
A dignified royal pincess
堂堂宗室王妃
was given away to the rebels by the Cui family.
竟被崔氏送给叛军
Stop!
住手
It was a misunderstanding.
误会 误会
What's wrong with you?
你怎么回事
This is Prince Qi, the current Regent.
此乃当朝监国岐王殿下
How dare you disrespect His Highness?
你竟敢对岐王殿下不敬
Have you completely forgotten
我崔氏的礼数
the etiquette observed by the Cui family?
你都记到狗肚子里去了
-I… -Go away!
我这 滚下去
Yes.
是
Your Highness is paying
殿下此来
this visit for the political marriage arranged for Princess Pingning, right?
是为平宁县主和亲一事吧
I know Your Highness can't bear to see the princess marry far away.
下官知道殿下不舍县主远嫁
But this political marriage is a major matter of state.
可和亲乃国家大事
The Cui family alone cannot interfere with it.
并非我崔氏一门之力可解
Do you mean the Cui family won't help me?
所以崔氏不想帮我
It's not that we refuse to help.
不是不想帮
It's just that we're unable to render any help.
实在是爱莫能助啊
Your Highness,
殿下
letting Princess Pingning get married for political purposes
其实令平宁县主和亲
could actually be
对您而言
a good thing for you.
未尝不是一件好事
Was Cangfeng Forge built for you?
这藏锋庐是给你造的吗
Are you in charge now?
你当家了
No...
不是
Did anyone say you could lend it to Xie Jiayu?
谁让你给谢嘉鱼用的
You even charged her rent.
还收租
What now?
干什么
Kicking me to the curb after using me, huh?
过河拆桥是不是
Let me ask you. Who exerted his utmost effort
我问你 是谁呕心沥血
and racked his brains
费尽心思
to help you keep that girl around?
帮你把那姑娘留下来的
So you taught Xie Jiayu how to smelt for refined iron.
是你教谢嘉鱼精铁冶炼的
Did I tell you to do that?
我让你教她精铁冶炼了吗
She made it.
造出来了
So soon?
这么快啊
How very gifted.
天赋异禀
She's a rare genius.
天降奇才
Xiao Wuyi, listen.
萧无衣 我跟你说
You must do whatever it takes to...
你一定要想尽办法把
This is not entirely my fault.
这事它也不能完全怪我
I simply gave her a rough idea.
我就是给提供了个思路
Your Highness.
世子
Prince Qi went to the Cui Mansion.
岐王去崔家了
What is he doing there?
去崔家做什么
How did it go?
如何
Did Chief Clerk Cui say yes?
崔长史允了
Let's go home.
我们回去吧
Master,
老师
I'd like to take a walk alone.
我想自己走走
Protect His Highness.
保护殿下
-Yes.
诺
Hurry, over there!
快 在那儿
We'd better not be late.
去晚了怕是要来不及了
This is truly a noble good deed.
这可是大功德呀
Princess Pingning is marrying into Northern Qin to safeguard Ye.
平宁县主为保大邺远嫁北秦
The imperial court plans to build a monument for her.
朝廷要给县主立碑
I'll lead the fundraising!
我带头筹钱
I'm going with you!
走 我也去
- Let's go!
走 走
-Let's all go! -Count me in!
一块儿去 我也去
Hurry up!
快点快点快点
-This is my share. -Come, guys!
这是我的 来来来
And this is my share.
这是我的
Count me in!
我也来
This is my share.
我的 我的
This is my share!
这我的
Take it all. I'm offering this much.
都拿去都拿去 这是我的
And here is my share.
这是我的
Count me in!
算我一个
Smash this place.
砸掉
We're also here to contribute.
我们也来捐
No pushing, please!
不要挤啊 不要挤
This is my share.
我的
I said, smash this place!
我说砸掉
Go away!
走开
No donation allowed!
不许捐
Grandma!
阿婆
It was who ordered them to break up the crowd.
是我让他们驱散那些百姓的
Yizhi,
易之
you shouldn't do things like that.
这些不是你该做的事
Then what should I do?
那我应该做什么
You hit a man in the Cui Mansion?
你在崔家打人了
Yes.
是
But I didn't feel pain at all.
但我一点都不觉得痛
It actually gave me a thrill.
我觉得痛快
I should have beaten him to death years ago.
我当年就该把他打死
When a man carries no weapon,
人在两手空空时
he can only fight with his bare hands.
只能以肉身相搏
That said, I'm also aware
但我也知道
there is only one way
要说服世家
to persuade the noble families.
其实只有一条路可以走
Let's bond through marriage.
联姻
Lingyi of the Cui family
崔女令仪
is a noble lady.
世家贵女
Having grown up as a bright child,
自幼聪慧
she is elegant in manners
举止娴雅
and refined in both appearance and character.
内外兼修
I swear to resort to any means to unite
臣必当殚精竭虑
all the major noble families
联合世家大族
to fight for a chance to get Your Highness and Princess Pingning
为岐王殿下 平宁县主
out of the current quagmire.
争得一线生机
From this day onward, we the Cui family
自今而后 我崔氏一门
pledge to stand together with Your Highness.
誓与殿下同心同德
Were there dangers ahead,
虽赴汤蹈火
we would not hesitate to aid Your Highness.
亦在所不辞
That day before the palace gate,
当日在宫门前
I misspoke in a moment of desperation.
是我情急之言
I know you have your own difficulties.
我知道你有你的难处
But since I am the Regent now,
但我既然当了这个监国
I shouldn't rely on you to help my own sister
就不能自己妹妹出了事
out of trouble.
还要你来相救
I will use my own strength
我会用我自己的力量
to protect those I want to protect.
去保护我想保护的人
I will also continue to promote reforms with you.
也会和你一起继续推行改制
Then what about Xie Jiayu?
那谢嘉鱼呢
I'll leave the choice to her.
我会让她自己选择
With Yaoyao's devotion to me,
夭夭对我之心
I'm sure she will stick around.
她一定会留下来的
But you just proposed to marry Ms. Cui.
可你刚求娶崔氏女
So what?
所以呢
Wuyi, when you asked for Yaoyao's hand in marriage,
无衣 你求娶夭夭之时
didn't you already have a wife?
难道没有世子妃吗
We both had to adopt expedients, right?
不都是权宜之计吗
How could you compare your situation with mine?
你与我如何相提并论
Xie Jiayu and I used to be strangers.
当初谢嘉鱼与我不过是陌路人
What's the difference?
有何不同
I asked to marry Ms. Cui
我娶崔氏女
only to save Lejun, didn't I?
不也是为了救乐君吗
Yaoyao loves me.
夭夭爱我
She will surely understand me.
她一定会理解我的
Li Yizhi,
李易之
you're even a worse bastard than I am.
你比我还要混蛋
You're right.
你说得不错
If being a good person
如果做好人
only turns me into a pawn,
只能被当成棋子的话
I'd rather be a villain.
那不如做个恶人
Someone said
某人说
she'd like to forge
要给你造一把
an unparalleled sword for you.
天下无双的宝剑
It must be extraordinarily sharp
要削铁如泥
and can be used as a saber.
要刀剑合一
It also has to be a hundred times better
还要比鹰王的龙阙宝刀
than the Eagle King's Longque Blade.
强一百倍
So, she asked me to teach her how to smelt for refined iron.
让我教她精铁冶炼
I just didn't know how to decline her request.
我也不知道该如何拒绝呀
What took you so long to say it?
不早说
Where is Xie Jiayu?
谢嘉鱼呢
Since the Young Lady's departure earlier today,
女郎白日出府后
she has not returned to Wensheng Courtyard yet.
就没再回过闻笙苑
This is bad.
坏了
Are you literally crying
也不至于我凶你两句
because I scolded you a bit?
你就哭吧
You almost exposed my military secrets,
你差点暴露我军中机密
and I haven't held you accountable yet.
我还没同你算账呢
Did you... temper with my portrait of a noble lady?
你动了我的仕女图
You...
你
As the dignified general of Beifu
你堂堂北府将军
and the Heir of Prince Jing'an,
靖安王世子
you appear to keep a distance from women,
表面上一副不近女色
but you're in fact stashing a portrait of a noble lady.
实际上你却偷偷藏仕女图
You have no scruples.
你丧心病狂
How is it any of your business?
关你何事
I am condemning you for...
我是替你
for your future darling.
未来的心上人谴责你
If there really is such a girl,
若真有此人
let her do it herself.
让她自己来
Hold on.
等等
Swords and blades are used by people.
人御刀剑
Shouldn't the length and form
长短形制
be designed based on
难道不需要参考
the user's height and arm length?
执剑者的身形臂长吗
Look at this sloppy draft.
这般潦草
Did you even put your heart into it?
到底用心与否
Why are you so demanding?
你怎么要求这么多啊
Is this how the Miraculous Craft does business?
妙手就是这么做生意的
You're receiving a gift.
你是收礼的
Why so picky?
还这么挑剔
This is just how I am.
我这人便是如此
I only accept gifts that are to my liking.
收礼要收到心坎上
If not, don't give any to me.
不然你就别送
Reach out your arms.
伸手
I don't have a tape measure here.
我这儿没有尺
Your hairband surely has many uses.
你的发带用处可真多
Yes.
是
It kills, too.
还能杀人呢
If you don't want to be taken by the Eagle King
你若不想被鹰王
to Northern Qin for hard labor,
拐去北秦做苦工
then don't slack off anymore during your practice
跟偃月练轻功的时候
of lightness skills with Yan Yue.
就别再偷懒
At least, they can help you escape when you get in danger.
遇到危险至少还能跑
Thanks to these skills,
天大地大
you'll be able to go anywhere alone
即便是你一个人
in this vast world.
也哪儿都能去
The visiting delegation
北秦太后
includes the Empress Dowager of Northern Qin.
也在这次来的使团之中
She and the Eagle King are after different benefits.
她与鹰王的利益不同
It's easier to halt the political marriage through her.
从她入手解决和亲更容易些
But before the peace talks complete,
但在和谈结束
and the Eagle King leaves Jiankang,
鹰王离开剑慷之前
you'd better stay away from him.
你给我离他远一点
Did you hear me?
听到没有
Yes, I heard you.
知道了
You're so nagging, just like my mother.
啰唆死了 跟我阿母似的
I want to see Mao.
我想见阿茂
No problem.
好
I'll tell him about it.
我来跟他说
My Lady, isn't Mount Ya
这崖山
the place that Prince Qi yearns
不是岐王殿下最想和女郎
to go with you most?
去的地方吗
Why is it crossed out?
怎么给划掉了
Mao probably
阿茂可能
won't go there with me.
不会跟我一起去了
My Lady, don't be upset.
女郎 你别难过了
I'll always be with you.
南星会永远陪着你的
I think I'm feeling something other than sadness.
但好像也不全是难过
Do you remember that trip along the river with lanterns?
你还记得我们游灯河那次吗
We wrote our wishes on small paper boats at that time.
我们把心愿写在小纸船上
I took a peek at Mao's.
我偷偷看了阿茂的心愿
He wrote
他写的是
that he hoped Lejun and Yaoyao's wishes would come true.
希望乐君和夭夭心愿得偿
Prince Qi has always been a nice gentleman
岐王殿下一直都是一个好人
who cares deeply about you and Princess Pingning.
将您和平宁县主放在心上
But he seems to never
但他好像
really have anything he truly wants.
从来没有自己想要的东西
I decided to run away from marriage,
我说逃婚
and he went with me.
他便跟着我逃了
Even though he has become the Regent,
哪怕他当上了监国
he's ready to leave with me as long as I want to.
我想走 他也愿意跟我走
But it seems I've never figured out
但我好像从来不知道
what Mao truly wants for himself.
阿茂自己想要什么
My Lady,
女郎
what do you want for yourself then?
那你自己想要什么呢
Xiao Wuyi treats you really well.
萧无衣对你可真好
You're not related to him or anything,
非亲非故的
yet he especially built a workshop
还特意在王府里面
for you in his own mansion.
给你弄了个工坊
It's midnight. Why did you
半夜不睡
come here instead of sleeping?
跑这儿来干吗
I can't sleep.
睡不着
Hearing the sounds here can soothe my mind.
听着这儿的声音静静心
This is a military secret.
军事机密啊
You want to see it? Ask me to be your master first.
要想看啊 先拜师
As if I care.
稀罕
I can make that myself.
我自己也会做
Those are blue fireworks.
是蓝色的
Yuan Xiaoliu, I can't believe you know how to make blue fireworks.
元小六 你竟然会做蓝色的烟花
I've never seen these before.
我以前竟然从未见过
The books only say that seashells make red fireworks,
书上只说加贝壳是红色
refined salt, yellow,
加精盐是黄色
silver powder, white,
加银粉是白色
and azurite, green.
加曾青是绿色
But blue fireworks...
但这蓝色
Yuan Xiaoliu, you are amazing.
元小六 你可真厉害
How come I never noticed it before?
以前怎么没发现呢
Blue fireworks
这个呀
were a plaything in my childhood.
是我儿时的玩乐之物
It is also the first type of fireworks
并且是我人生中做的
I've ever made in my life.
第一个烟花
How do I compare to you?
比你如何
You're impressive.
你厉害
But I just won't ask you to be my master.
但我就是不拜你为师
What can you do about it?
你能奈我何
Why not use the lightness skills I taught you?
教你的轻功呢
Add two more sandbags to the training,
明日再加两包沙袋
and practice for four more hours tomorrow.
再多练两个时辰
Did you hear me?
听到没有
Yes, I got it.
我知道了
I won't be like this anymore.
我下次再也不这样了
Take this.
给你
His Majesty is too soft,
陛下太软弱了
and shouldn't have agreed
就不应该给萧无衣
to grant Xiao Wuyi any time to reform Beifu.
北府改制的时间
I know you've never approved of these peace talks.
吾知你一直不认可此次和谈
But if you hadn't underestimated the enemy
但若不是你轻敌
and lost a battle at Jiuzhang Plain,
兵败九丈原
these peace talks
今日或许
would probably be avoided.
根本不需要这场和谈
Given that the emperor is too young,
陛下年纪尚轻
and you're holding much military power,
你又手握重兵
I demand you to promise me
吾要你保证
that even after my passing,
即便吾死后
you will still be of one mind with the emperor.
你也必须和陛下一条心
Yes, I promise.
诺
He really is hiding in Jiankang.
他果然就藏在剑慷城内
Your Majesty.
太后
Where were the fireworks set off?
这烟花出自何处
Your Majesty,
回禀太后
the fireworks were set off in Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
这烟花出自靖安王府
Xiao Wuyi...
萧无衣
I thought Your Majesty
我以为太后
would never take my advice.
听不进在下的忠告
I will, provided that you agree
除非世子答应吾
to find someone for me.
帮吾找一个人
Who is it?
什么人
I saw a burst of blue fireworks last night.
昨夜吾看到一束蓝烟花
That must be the work of an old acquaintance of mine.
必是出自吾一位故人之手
Those fireworks...
那烟花
were set off in Prince Jing'an's Mansion,
来自靖安王府
made by Mulian Ying...
穆连婴
the very last survivor of the Mulian clan.
穆连一族最后的余孽
I've spent 20 years looking for him.
吾找了他二十年
Little did I expect him to be in your hands, Young Lord Xiao.
没想到在世子手中
Mulian Ying...
穆连婴
How did you come up with the idea
你是怎么想到
of triggering the fuse with mercury?
用水银触发引线
And you fancy being my master.
亏你还想当我师父
Your fireworks suddenly exploded
你那烟花突然引爆
and almost injured me.
差点伤到我
Mercury is light in weight and stable in nature.
这水银其质轻便 又很稳定
It won't kindle fire no matter how you shake it.
无论如何晃动也不会引爆
Besides, once the mechanism is activated...
而且啊 一旦触发这个机关
Look.
你看
How is it?
怎么样
Ignited, isn't it?
是不是引燃了
What's with you?
你怎么了
Nothing.
没事
Impressive.
厉害
You're way more talented than I am.
你的天赋远高于我呀
You will surely
日后
become a legendary master one day.
你一定会成为一代宗师
I am so flattered.
过誉了 过誉了
You must take me as your master.
你必须得拜我为师
If necessary,
实在不行
I can take you as my master.
我拜你为师也可以
Then, the two of us,
这样
a duo of master and disciple,
你我师徒二人
will work together to make
一同打造一个
an unparalleled caltrop fireball.
举世无双的火蒺藜
In my mind right now,
我现在这脑海里啊
I'm already picturing us,
已经浮现出你我师徒二人
as master and disciple, leaving our mark in history.
名垂青史的景象了
Come on, why is this act again?
我说 你怎么又来了
I helped you
我帮你
simply to honor
是因为这烟花
my promise to Xiao Wuyi.
是我答应萧无衣的
He told me the Empress Dowager of Northern Qin
他说北秦太后
saw the blue fireworks we set off that night
看到了咱们那晚放的蓝色烟花
and liked them a lot.
很是喜欢
So she asked Xiao Wuyi to give her some
让萧无衣送她一些
to take back to Northern Qin.
她好带回北秦
How could I let such an important gift
这么重要的和谈之礼
for the peace talks easily explode?
怎么能随便就炸了呢
You just mentioned the Empress Dowager of Northern Qin?
你刚才说北秦太后
Do you know her?
你认识她
Me?
我
How could I possibly know the Empress Dowager of Northern Qin?
我怎么可能认识北秦太后呢
I mean,
我的意思是
she holds such an exalted status.
北秦太后的身份那么尊贵
What brings her to this place?
她来咱们这儿干吗
It's said that she's looking for a man named Mulian Ying.
说是要找一个叫穆连婴的人
Recently, Xiao Wuyi has also sent Qing Long and Yan Yue
萧无衣最近也让青龙 偃月
to search for this man.
在找此人
When this person is found,
若是能找到此人
the marriage arranged for Lejun can be called off.
那乐君的婚就能退了
Xiao Wuyi doesn't even know who Mulian Ying is.
萧无衣又不认识穆连婴
How is he supposed to find him?
他怎么找啊
I heard that he was given a portrait of this man.
好像说是给了一个画像
It is how the man looked as a teenager, though.
不过是十几岁时的模样
The draft for the caltrop fireball is beneath the stack.
火蒺藜的图纸是下面那张
Oh, thanks.
谢谢啊
You were not fainted?
你没晕啊
You really are the man,
果然是你
Mulian Ying.
穆连婴
The Empress Dowager of Northern Qin has been looking for you.
北秦太后一直在找你
So you used me, Xiao Wuyi.
萧无衣 你利用我
You knew all along that Yuan Xiaoliu is Mulian Ying.
你早就知道元小六就是穆连婴
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
when did you find out who I am?
你是什么时候知道我身份的
On the day I saved you,
自从我第一天救你
I knew you were from Northern Qin.
我就知你是北秦人
It just didn't cross my mind that you're Mulian Ying.
只是没想过你会是这个身份
Over these years, the Northern Qin spies'
这些年北秦暗探
top priority in Jiankang
在剑慷的第一要务
has always been finding Mulian Ying.
就是寻找穆连婴
The Empress Dowager of Northern Qin is in Jiankang right now
北秦太后如今就在剑慷
as a member of the delegation.
她就在这次来的使团中
Mulian Ying and I were once in love.
吾曾与穆连婴两情相悦
However, the palace lanterns burn long, casting light on the iron warrant.
奈何宫灯长明映铁券
The bounds of the inner court are like a moat to heaven.
宫闱之限如天堑
Despite all those great ambitions he had,
他纵有鹰扬万里志
the then emperor saw him as a potential hazard.
却成了帝王肉中刺
I thought I could at least keep him alive.
吾本以为至少可以护他性命
But unexpectedly,
可谁料
I ended up causing the destruction of his entirely clan.
却给他招来了灭门之祸
Being plagued by an old illness,
吾旧疾缠身
my life is coming to an end.
命不久矣
I hope you can find him for me,
想让你帮吾找找他
so I can see him one last time before I pass,
在吾离开之前跟他见上一面
and clear up all these old grievances.
了却这段恩怨
What did you just say?
你刚才说什么
What did you mean by "her life is coming to an end"?
什么叫命不久矣
If you are that worried,
你若是担心
I will take you to see her directly.
我直接带你去见她
How do you know if she's after Yuan Xiaoliu's life?
你怎知她不是来杀元小六的
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
are you doing this for yourself,
你是为了你自己
or for me?
还是为了我啊
I can not only help Li Lejun regain her freedom,
吾不但可以还李乐君自由
but also form an alliance
而且吾会力排鹰王之意
between Northern Qin and Southern Ye against the Eagle King's will,
让北秦和南邺形成盟友
thus preventing years of war.
免去连年征战
What do you think, Young Lord Xiao?
世子以为如何
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
you promised me you'd help Lejun.
你答应过我会帮乐君
Now the Empress Dowager wants to see Yuan Xiaoliu.
太后想见他
This is our only chance.
这是唯一的机会
No, I can't hand over Yuan Xiaoliu.
元小六不行
This is a risk I will not take.
这个险我不会冒
I won't let her kill you,
我不会让她杀你
nor will I let you kill her.
更不会让你杀她
Over these years, you've been hiding your identity
这些年你隐匿身份
and producing weapons in Beifu
在北府制造武器
to fight Northern Qin.
对抗北秦
Isn't it because
难道不是因为你
you're still holding hatred in your heart?
从未放下心中仇恨吗
Do you think she's asking to meet you
你以为她想与你见面
just to do some catching up with you?
只是为了叙旧情吗
Take him away.
把人带走
Go back to your place.
你先回去吧
I will figure something out.
我会想办法的
Is everything up for negotiation
是不是在你们的大局之下
for your so-called greater good?
所有事都可以被权衡
And after being weighed,
而被权衡过后
those who are hurt and sacrificed
受伤害的 被牺牲的
will always be us, right?
永远只有我们
The marriages arranged
我 乐君
for me, Lejun,
元姬阿姊 我阿母
Sister Yuanji, and my mother,
我们所有人的婚姻
are about schemes and manipulation.
只有算计和利用
Nobody cares about true love.
没有人在乎真心
If given another chance,
再给你一次机会
you would still marry Ms. He
你还是会为了粮草
for military provisions,
同意娶何氏之女
ask the Empress Dowager to grant a marriage
还是会为了逼长沙王
so as to pressure Prince Changsha,
求太后赐婚
and still place Lejun
还是会把乐君
at the very end of all considerations.
放在一切考量的最后
This is what you're like,
这就是你
Xiao Wuyi.
萧无衣
Not just you,
不只是你
Mao has changed too.
阿茂也变了
He already started selecting concubines for himself.
他已经开始选妃了
He has decided to stay,
他决定留下
yet he hasn't told me.
却没有告诉我
I'm well aware of it,
我明明知道
but I'm still arguing
却还在这里
relentlessly with you about Lejun's marriage.
为了乐君的婚事与你争执不休
You must be laughing at me in your heart.
你一定在心里嘲笑我吧
You are right.
你说得没错
If given another chance,
再来一次
I would still make the same choices.
我依然会如此
But I will never laugh at you.
但我永远不会嘲笑你
I am sick and tired
我对权衡
of all that weighing.
厌烦透顶
I will not give up.
我不会放弃
I will not let Lejun end up like me.
我不会让乐君和我一样
Princess Pingning shall enter the hall.
平宁县主上殿
I, Li Lejun, Princess Pingning, extend
平宁县主李乐君
my greetings to Your Majesty.
叩见吾皇
Long live
吾皇万岁
Your Majesties.
太后千岁
Your Highness?
侧妃
Yuan Xiaoliu, come out!
元小六 出来
Yuan Xiaoliu is not in this carriage.
这车里哪有什么元小六
He already boarded a ship and left.
元小六已经上船走了
Yuan Xiaoliu, I know you are inside, and that you're still
元小六 我知道你在里面
still thinking about the Empress Dowager of Northern Qin.
也知你心中放不下北秦太后
Her heart disease is incurable,
她的心疾已无药可医
and her days are numbered.
时日无多
If you leave now,
你若是走了
you might never get to see her again in the rest of your life.
怕是此生再也不能与她相见
Listen up. Tonight,
告诉你 今夜
I've arranged a Northern Qin puppet show
我在西月楼排了一出
in Xiyue Restaurant.
北秦的傀儡戏
It is up to you whether to go or not.
去不去就看你的了
You'd hate to have regrets for a lifetime, right?
你也不想抱憾终生吧
Yuan Xiaoliu.
元小六
Mr. Yuan, do not act rashly.
元先生切勿轻举妄动
It's His Highness's order
世子有令
that you will be executed
若元先生不从
on the spot if you defy the command.
就地斩杀
All the 138 members of the Yuan clan
我元氏一百三十八口
died because of that woman.
皆因她而死
I severed ties with her long ago.
我早与她恩断义绝
Now, hearing that she is about to die,
今听闻她人之将死
I only feel the pleasure of having my greatest revenge fulfilled.
我心中只有大仇得报的快感
I will never
我是不会再与她
see her again.
相见的
Qing Long,
青龙
let's go.
咱们走
You really came.
你还真来了
If Xiao Wuyi finds out about this,
这要是让萧无衣知道了
I will...
那我
Don't worry.
你放心
I promise to save your life with mine today.
今日我定以命相救
If the Empress Dowager of Northern Qin
如果北秦太后
truly attempts to hurt you,
真的要对你动手
I will shield you
我一定会挡在你身前
and let you go first.
让你先走
You have my word.
这是我对你的承诺
Xiao Wuyi will be furious then.
那萧无衣得气死了
What did you say?
你说什么
Nothing.
没说什么
I mean,
我是说
are you really planning
你真的为了阻止
to risk your life for the cancellation
那个李乐君的婚约
of Li Lejun's marriage?
不惜赌上自己的性命
Isn't this
朋友之间
what friends do for each other?
不就应该是这样的吗
Moved by your chivalry,
就冲你这份侠义
I've decided to stand or fall together with you tonight.
今夜你我共进退
Today is your wedding day.
今日乃你大喜之日
Prince Qi claimed to be sick and took leave from court.
岐王称病不朝
Young Lord Xiao hasn't shown up either.
萧世子也未曾现身
Could it be that the two of them
莫不是他二人
are dissatisfied with this marriage
对这门婚事不满
and are working together to object it for you?
联手为你拒婚不成
It doesn't matter now.
罢了
The auspicious hour has arrived.
吉时已到
His Highness the Eagle King
请鹰王殿下
and Princess Pingning shall perform the bowing ceremony.
和平宁县主行交拜礼
Eagle King, please bow.
请鹰王行礼
Princess Pingning, please bow.
请县主行礼